This is probably the most
interesting chart in all of physics.
First thing you'll probably notice is
that there is this diagonal line with
humans and whales and viruses
and planets and stars.
So it's something related
to mass and size, right?
But on the other hand, if you look
at here, you have particles and this
last axis is all about energy.
And if you go up, you have those
diagonal lines and here it says now on
all those numbers there are measures
in seconds so what is happening so
let me take you through the triangle
of everything anything that can ever
exist in the universe and the history
of time fits here so let's start by
trying to understand what is it?
And the best place to
start is by looking at us.
This is us, humans. We are not in the
center of the chart, we are sort of
a little above the center.
So in this chart the horizontal axis
represents the size of things and the
vertical axis represents the mass.
So right here just by looking at
water you understand why everything is
in a line because one liter of water
is roughly a cube 10 centimeters wide.
One ton of water, which is a thousand
times the mass, will be one meter,
which is 10 times the size.
So this is why everything is
sort of this diagonal line.
This blue line you see here, that is
the line of the density of water and
everything that is on the right of
the chart is something that will float
on water. On the left side
are things that are heavier.
For example, here's an interesting
story, the hippo is right on the chart
because the hippo actually cannot swim,
it doesn't float in water, it just
walks and as you see and go up the
line and notice that most of the stuff
here is to the left side. And most,
those data points is mostly meteorites
and meteors. And if you go up, we
leave the living things and start going
into engineering projects and small
asteroids and then the great pyramid.
And then we have
asteroids and small moons.
And you'll notice that they're all on
the left side, meaning they're heavy,
they're made of iron, they're on up,
you notice something interesting starts
to happen, which is they get rounder
and rounder and rounder and when we
reach Pluto, we can notice
that it's a perfect sphere.
What's happening is that gravity simply
overcomes the molecular forces that
bind everything together and therefore
the object just starts acting as
a liquid and just
becomes a perfect sphere.
So everything now will be round because
the strongest force here is gravity.
And as we increase the gravity,
something else also starts happening.
We also increase atmosphere.
Mercury has no atmosphere, Mars has
a very thin atmosphere, Venus, Earth,
now we have like a strong atmosphere,
but when you go up, we reach the gas
giants. That's because Earth sits in
a very thin line between not having
enough gravity to hold gases around
it, or having so much gravity that it
just attracts everything
and becomes a gas giant.
We have four gas giants
in our solar system.
And as they become larger and larger,
suddenly something weird happens.
Notice the Saturn is on the right side
of the line, that's because Saturn
is actually as dense as styrofoam.
If you could find a pool of water
large enough, you could take a little
bit of Saturn and it would float on it.
Then we start seeing that the trend
is that most of the stars start going
on the other line, and for the first
time they start diverging from the
line, they are compressing.
What is happening here is that the
force of gravity and the pressure in
the core is so strong that matter
starts becoming degenerate matter.
And it starts stripping away the atoms
and starts crushing the atoms together
and the atoms will start
generating a little bit of energy.
And when they start generating energy,
they will now have an outside pressure,
that is the energy of the fusion of the
atoms, and as they create this energy,
they start expanding the sizes of those
entities again, and those will become
stars. So stars, like the sun, they're
always in this one giant line, which
is called the main sequence star.
And here we will see actually the life
cycle of a star, but that expansion
has a cost. In order for stars to keep
their size, they need to spend fuel,
and that fuel is hydrogen.
And when they run out of helium, first
they will expand as they shed their
outer layers and they become red giants,
and then sometimes they will collapse
a few times and expand again until they
will often just go boom and a supernova
is a rapidly expanding cloud of gas
which will push the object very far
to the right. Actually, it will split
the object, most of the mass will
just expand outwards, and the inner
core will collapse into some special
object. Depending on the mass, it
might become a white dwarf, or if they
are massive enough, they will become
a neutron star, and if they are more
massive, they will just
collapse into black holes.
And this line right here is
the Schwarzschild radius.
And the Schwarzschild radius is the first
limit of our triangle of everything.
There's a point in which every object,
doesn't matter its size or mass,
will collapse into a black hole.
For any object there is a compression
point in which you just cross the
Schwarzschild radius and it
will become a black hole.
A black hole has no really defined
size because scientists consider that
everything in the center just collapsed
into singularity of size zero.
But there is a Schwarzschild radius and
that radius is the point of no return
where nothing that goes inside
of it can ever come back.
And that radius is directly proportional
to the mass, meaning that that's
why the slope here is a one-to-one
slope, it's a 45-degree angle.
The more massive your black hole
becomes, the larger it becomes.
And really, black holes can have any size.
Right here we are looking at black holes
with the mass of stars, but anything
can become a black hole. It's not easy
for some object to become a black
hole and they need to have
the certain conditions.
And we know that those conditions
happen when stars collapse, but we also
know that those same conditions have
happened before in the early universe.
So it is very possible that in the
early universe, lots of black holes have
been formed. Most of them will have
evaporated by now due to Hawking radiation.
but there could be some left over.
And if there are any of those primordial
black holes around, they would
be roughly the mass of a small moon,
but compressed to the size of a tiny
atom. Can you imagine how you can see
an atom just zipping around the galaxy
in the middle of space? You cannot
observe such an object with a telescope.
It's just too small and too far away, so
it would be an object that is invisible
to the eye, but you could detect it
only because of its effects on gravity.
You might think that this sounds a lot
like dark matter, and a lot of scientists
would agree with you, and that's why
primordial black holes are actually
one of the possible
candidates for dark matter.
You notice that beyond the scale of
stars, every object will follow a second
diagonal line, which is
a separate density line.
It's a much lighter density, and
that's the density of dark matter.
And that's the density of supernovas
and stellar nurseries and globular
clusters and dwarf galaxies.
And our own galaxy, it's right here.
And then of groups of galaxies,
and then of galaxy clusters.
And then we'll have the super filaments,
like the one we live on called
Laniakea, which are filaments made of
super groups, made of groups, made
of galaxies, which are made of stars.
And then the only object
beyond those are just voids.
Just areas in space who are
completely devoid of stars.
But yet they do have mass.
We know they have mass because
their effects on gravity.
And we actually think that their mass
puts them in the same diagonal as
everything else here. There's a point
in which nothing can be bigger than
that. And we reach the second side
of our triangle of everything, which
is the Hubble radius. The Hubble radius
is the limit at which anything can
be seen by us. It's based on the speed
of light and the rate of expansion
of the universe. Nothing can be bigger
than the Hubble radius because anything
outside the Hubble radius cannot ever
be seen by us or interact with us
in any way. It is not
the size of the universe.
The size of the universe is, as far
as we know, infinite, but that is our
universe, that is the observable universe.
And if we try to calculate how much
mass we believe our universe has and
plot in this chart, it will be right on
the intersection of the Schwarzschild
radius and the Hubble radius.
Which seems to be a very interesting
coincidence, because the observable
universe is a bubble in which nothing can
escape and everything on the Schwarzschild
radius are black holes for
which nothing can come out.
Does that mean that our universe
is itself a black hole?
Probably not. probably the observable
universe was not always on the Schwarzschild
radius. Also the black holes are round
and they have a singularity in the
center. And our observable universe is
only round from Earth's perspective.
Someone in another place would see a
different size of universe, so it's
not as if everything is locked.
Someone in the edges of our universe
would be able to see other stuff, they
just would never be able
to communicate that to us.